<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life-guard of a loyall Christian, described in a sermon, preached at St Peters Corn-hill, upon Sunday in the afternoone, May 7. 1648. / By Paul Knell, Master in Arts of Clare-Hall in Cambridge: sometimes chaplaine to a regiment of curiasiers in his Majesties Army.</title>
            <author>Knell, Paul, 1615?-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E444_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204196</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863867</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863867</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87808)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 70:E444[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life-guard of a loyall Christian, described in a sermon, preached at St Peters Corn-hill, upon Sunday in the afternoone, May 7. 1648. / By Paul Knell, Master in Arts of Clare-Hall in Cambridge: sometimes chaplaine to a regiment of curiasiers in his Majesties Army.</title>
                  <author>Knell, Paul, 1615?-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XLIII, 2 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Life-Guard OF <hi>A Loyall Chriſtian,</hi> deſcribed in A SERMON, PREACHED At St <hi>Peters Corn-hill,</hi> upon Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in the afternoone, <hi>May</hi> 7. 1648.</p>
            <p>BY PAUL KNELL, Maſter in Arts of Clare-Hall in <hi>Cambridge:</hi> Sometimes Chaplaine to a Regiment of <hi>Curiaſiers</hi> in his Majeſties Army.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ROM. 8.31.</bibl>
               <p>If God be for us, who can be againſt us?</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Yeare 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:161734:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:161734:2"/>
            <head>A Prayer for the King.</head>
            <p>O Lord, preſerve the Kings moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, our Soveraign Lord <hi>Charles,</hi> King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, and Supream Governour in theſe his Realms, and in all other his Dominions and Countreys, over all perſons, and in all Cauſes, as well Eccleſiaſticall as Temporall. Behold, O God our Defender, and look upon the face of thine Anoynted; Lord remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber King <hi>Charles,</hi> and all his troubles, remember him according to the favour that thou beareſt unto thy people; O viſit him with thy ſalvation, plead thou his Cauſe, O Lord, with them that ſtrive with him, and fight thou againſt them that have ſo long fought againſt thee and him; thou that bringeſt man out of priſon, be pleaſed to bring him thence, deliver him not alwayes over unto the will of his Enemies, but ſet his feet once more in a large roome; ſend down thine hand from above, deliver him, and take him out of the great waters, from the hand of ſtrange children, keep him as the apple of thine eye, hide him under the ſhaddow of thy wings, from the men of thy hand, O Lord, from the men and from the evill world, let
<pb facs="tcp:161734:3"/>his honour yet be great in thy ſalvation; glory and great worſhip doe thou lay upon him, ſet his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion alſo in the Sea, and his right hand in the Floods; as for thoſe his Trayterous Enemies, which would not that he ſhould reign over them, though they have imagined ſuch a device, let them never be able to perform it, but let them all be ſubdued unto him even in the midſt among the Kings Enemies; Let us no longer ſee ſervants upon horſes, and Princes walking as ſervants upon the earth; but they that now trample upon him, let them kneel before him, let his Enemies lick the duſt; comfort him again now after the time that thou haſt afflicted him, and for the years wherein he hath ſeen ſo much evill, reſtore him to his Crown on earth, and when thou takeſt away this, give him a Crown in heaven.</p>
            <closer>And let every Loyall Chriſtian ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161734:3"/>
            <head>The Life-Guard OF <hi>A Loyall Chriſtian.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ISAIAH 43.2.</bibl>
                  <p>When thou paſſeſt thorow the waters, I will be with thee; and thorow the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee: when thou walkeſt thorow the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>em miſerum video, hominem ſcio;</hi> trouble is the very badge and cognizance of humanity; we are born to it, holy <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, as the ſparks flie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; to this end were we borne, and for this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161734:4"/>cauſe came we into the world. Or if this be not <hi>finit intentionis,</hi> yet it is <hi>finit executionis,</hi> I am ſure, if we came not hither a purpoſe to be troubled, yet without great trouble we cannot get from hence, from the Cradle to the Coffin, being like <hi>Ezekiels</hi> roule, full of Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and mourning, and woe. There are ſome indeed (I meane the Trayterous Reformers of our Age) that live wholly at eaſe in their uſurped Poſſeſſions, they come in no miſ-fortune like other Folke, neither are they plagued like other men: But theſe look like the Devils Darlings, or rather like the Worlds Baſtards; though we may be men therefore without trouble, yet without it we cannot be Loyall Subjects, we cannot be good Chriſtians; <hi>in the world yee ſhall have tribulation,</hi> were the words of our departing Saviour to his Church. But he told them juſt before, <hi>that in him they ſhould have peace,</hi> and he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them in effect the ſelfe-ſame in our Text, <hi>That he will deliver them in ſix troubles;</hi> yea, <hi>that in ſeven there ſhall no evill touch them; that in Famine hee will redeem them from death, and in Warre from the power of the Sword;</hi> Let their troubles bee externall, corporall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, let their troubles bee internall, ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, yet their <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and their <hi>Iehovah</hi> will deliver them out of all; <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorough the waters, I will bee with thee; and thorow the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee; when thou walkeſt thorow the fire, thou ſhalt not bee burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words, ye may pleaſe to obſerve with me four parts, the Paſſenger, the Paſſage, the Concomitant, and the Conſequent. The Paſſenger is the Church, <hi>cum tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieris,</hi> when thou paſſeſt. The Paſſage is twofold, <hi>per aquas &amp; per ignes,</hi> thorough waters, and thorough fire. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant or the Convoy, is Almighty God, <hi>tibi ad ſum,</hi> I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161734:4"/>am or I will be with thee. The Conſequent, is the Churches ſafety, <hi>flumina non operient, flamma non incendet,</hi> the rivers ſhall not overflow thee, the flame ſhall not kindle on thee. And of theſe parts in order. I begin with the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, which is the Church, <hi>cum tranſieris,</hi> when thou paſſeſt.</p>
            <p>Had we retained our firſt integrity, we might eaſily have ſtept to heaven with as great facility as from one room to another, from the parlour of an earthly, to the preſence-chamber of an heavenly Paradiſe. But ſinne hath placed a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a great gulf between us and heaven; we that were ſometimes near, are now afarre off; whoſoever will hereafter enter into <hi>Canaan,</hi> he muſt undergo a tedious paſſage tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the wilderneſſe.</p>
            <p>There are foure titles that pertain to the beſt of <hi>Adams</hi> ſons, <hi>Advenae, Inquilini, Hoſpites, Peregrini,</hi> we are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, we are ſojourners, we are gueſts, we are pilgrims; but of all foure, the laſt, me thinks, fitteth our condition beſt, <hi>Peregrini,</hi> we are pilgrims, <hi>Viatores,</hi> we are travellers, <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euntes,</hi> we are paſſengers, here we have no continuing city, but we ſeek for one to come. Look upon the Patriarch <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> the great grandfather of the Church, and ye ſhall finde him like St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in journeying often; from <hi>Caldea</hi> to <hi>Charran,</hi> from <hi>Charran</hi> to <hi>Canaan,</hi> where he jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyed, the Apoſtle telleth us, as in a ſtrange countrey, dwelling in Tabernacles with <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob;</hi> he had there none inheritance, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> no not ſo much as to ſet his foot on, to teach him and us all, that we muſt not ſet up our ſtaffe here, <hi>plus ultra,</hi> we muſt go further, we being but Pilgrims on the earth.</p>
            <p>This we know likewiſe to have been the condition of the Iſraelites, who wandered in the wilderneſſe in a ſolitary way, and found no city to dwell in; their own houſes were tents, Gods houſe was but a Tabernacle, all portable, to be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161734:5"/>carried up and down from one place to another; they had neither tenement nor Temple, till they were ſetled in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> nor have we any certain dwelling place, till we come thither where the Lamb's the Temple. For while we are at home in the body, we are not properly at home, we are but <hi>in viâ,</hi> in the way that leadeth us to it; we are born from above, and therefore there is our native coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; all the while we are on earth, we are, as it were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a pilgrimage to heaven. And the application of this now may be twofold.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſeeing we are but paſſengers here and pilgrims, this may ſerve to ſet ſpurs to us, and haſten us toward our countrey. For no paſſenger would willingly tarry long upon the way, but maketh all the haſte he can to get him home. So let us think it our greateſt puniſhment (next to this Rebellious Reformation) that we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to dwell with <hi>Meſech,</hi> to have our habitation among the tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> and therefore wiſh, with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>David, To have the wings of a Dove,</hi> that ſo wee might flie home to heaven, and be at reſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, though here we are but paſſengers, yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heaven is our home, this may comfort us amidſt all our plunderings and perſecutions, all our neceſſities and diſtreſſes. For let a paſſenger meet with never ſo bad entertainment by the way, yet hee will not greatly murmure at it; I have better at home, hee will ſay, and it will not be long, I hope, ere I get thither. So, brethren, as long as there are quarters taken up for us in heaven, if we have any Chriſtian courage, let us not faint by the way, be our uſage never ſo courſe, be our paſſage never ſo perillous;</p>
            <p>Which leadeth me from the firſt part of the Text, the Paſſenger, the Church; to the ſecond, which is her Paſſage, and this I finde to be two-fold, <hi>per aquas, &amp; per ignes,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:161734:5"/>thorow waters, and thorow fire. Her firſt paſſage is <hi>per aquas, when thou paſſeſt thorow the waters.</hi> Which <hi>waters</hi> have ſundry ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions in holy Scripture: the literall is firſt in nature, and muſt be ſo in order. And <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi> will have an <hi>Alleotheta</hi> here, one tenſe put for another, <hi>tranſieris,</hi> for <hi>tranſibas, when thou paſſeſt,</hi> or <hi>ſhalt paſſe,</hi> inſtead of <hi>when thou paſſedſt,</hi> or <hi>didſt paſſe,</hi> alluding to the paſſage of <hi>Noah</hi> in the <hi>deluge,</hi> or rather to that of <hi>Iſrael</hi> thorow the <hi>Red Sea.</hi> But whether this, or no, be the meaning, theſe examples ſuite well with the Text; and of the ſame nature we have ſome other in holy writ, the example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> of the Diſciples, of Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> I ſhall anon touch upon theſe in their proper place, I ſhall here only ſhew you the ſeverall acceptions of theſe waters, the literall I have briefly poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at already.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by <hi>waters</hi> we may underſtand the enemies of the Church. So they are expreſſed by holy <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 88.17. <hi>They came round about me daily like water, and compaſſed me together on every ſide.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.7. he prayeth after this manner, <hi>Send down thine hand from above, deliver me, and take me out of the great waters, from the hand of ſtrange Children.</hi> And <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.15. the Angel expounding the viſion of the great whore, which ſate upon many waters, telleth Saint <hi>John</hi> in expreſſe words; <hi>The wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which thou ſaweſt, where the whore ſitteth, they are peoples, and multitudes, and nations, and tongues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by <hi>waters</hi> we may underſtand hereſies, and doctrine of devills, (which are too common, ſince we had neither King nor Biſhop.) So <hi>Aretius</hi> and others expound that, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.15. where we read that <hi>the Serpent caſt out of his mouth, water as a flood, after the woman, that he might cauſe her to be carried away of the flood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, by <hi>waters</hi> we may underſtand the abyſſe of deſperation. So we may conſtrue that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 69. <hi>The waters are come in even unto my ſoul,</hi> verſe 1. <hi>I am come into deep waters,</hi> verſe 2. <hi>Let not the water-flood drowne me,</hi> ver. 16.</p>
            <p>The Churches ſecond paſſage is <hi>per ignes, when thou walkeſt thorow the fire.</hi> Which is firſt literally to be taken, and we have examples of ſome in Scripture that found a ſafe paſſage thorow this fire, as <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the Iſraelites, and the three Children.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:161734:6"/>
            <p>Secondly, by <hi>fire</hi> we are to underſtand perſecution and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſalme</hi> 66. <hi>Thou laydeſt trouble upon our loynes, ingreſſi ſumus per ignem, we went thorow the ſire.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> uſeth the ſame Metaphor, <hi>Think it not ſtrange concerning the fiery triall which is to trie you.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.12.</p>
            <p>The reſult then of all, is briefly this, That <hi>it is the portion of the Church to paſſe thorow fire and water,</hi> it is her deſtiny to ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and affliction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark was a notable repreſentation of the Church, that was toſſed upon the waves in the generall inundation, ſo is this in the worlds troubled ſea which cannot reſt. The diſciples ſhip, in the Goſpell, was another figure of the Church, that was covered with waves, almoſt overwhelmed with a raging tempeſt; ſo this is filled with the ſcornful reproof of the wealthy, the deep waters of the proud are ready to runne even over her ſoul. The Church is a Ship, the World is the Sea; <hi>a ſea of glaſſe mingled with fire,</hi> Revel. 15.2. Of <hi>glaſſe,</hi> there is the brittle and inconſtant conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world; <hi>mingled with fire,</hi> here are the troubles of the Church, St. <hi>Peters</hi> fiery triall. Troubled, alas! ſhe is, and ſo hath ever been. Look upon <hi>Jacob,</hi> look upon <hi>Joſeph,</hi> upon <hi>David,</hi> upon the Son of <hi>David.</hi> The time would fail me to tell you of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, of the Martyrs, Confeſſours, and other holy men of God, how they paſſed thorow the waters, how they wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thorow the fire; how they had triall of cruell mockings and ſcourgings; yea, moreover alſo of bonds and impriſonment; how they were <hi>ſtoned,</hi> as S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> how they were <hi>ſawne aſunder,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> how they were <hi>ſlaine with the ſword,</hi> as the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul;</hi> how they were <hi>beheaded,</hi> as St. <hi>John Baptiſt; Strafford and Canterbury;</hi> how they were hanged, as <hi>Tomkins, Chaloner, Yeomans, Bourchiar, Burleigh,</hi> and others; how they wandred about in deſarts and mountaines, and in dens, and caves of the earth, in ſheep-skins and goat-skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented. Thus we ſee, that all which will be Loyall to God and the King, all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution. Till our Saviour came into the Ship, the Sea was <hi>calme</hi> and <hi>quiet,</hi> but when he was once aboard, there <hi>ſtraightway aroſe a mighty tempeſt.</hi> So long then as thou art without Chriſt, or without God in this world, the devill will make fair weather
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161734:6"/>round about thee, but when once Chriſt Jeſus is, as it were, come aboard thy ſoul, then will Satan raiſe a ſtorme to try if he can make ſhip-wrack of thy faith; when thou haſt liſted thy ſelfe a Souldier to fight under thy Saviours and thy Soveraigns Banner, then look for a whole ſhower of fiery arrowes from the wicked one, for the <hi>meſſenger of Satan</hi> to <hi>buffet</hi> thee, with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> both by <hi>inward temptations,</hi> and <hi>outward tribulations,</hi> by private ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and publick perſecutions, the Devill will ſtrive to ſplit thee againſt the rock of deſperation. But take this for thy comfort, that although thou art dangerouſly toſſed, yet thou ſhalt not be caſt away, for even he that upholdeth the heaven is thine upholder. Which leadeth me from the ſecond part of the Text, the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches paſſage thorow <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>water,</hi> to the third, which is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant, or the convoy, Almighty God, <hi>Tibi adſum, I am,</hi> or <hi>I will be with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I that am the great Creator of Heaven and Earth; I that fill all places, and am contained in none; I that am about thy path, and about thy bed, and ſpie out all thy wayes, <hi>tibi adſum, I am, I will be with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what need then is there of this promiſe? For we may ſay it without blaſphemy, that God muſt ſtill be with us; it being as impoſſible for him to deny his omnipreſence, as to deny himſelf, he can ſooner ſeparate heat from fire, he did that in <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Furnace; he can ſooner ſeparate light from the Sun, he did this at our Saviours expiration; the Creator can better doe any thing, then divorce or divide his preſence from his Creatures, for herein not only our <hi>bene eſſe,</hi> but our very <hi>eſſe</hi> doth conſiſt, ſhould he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract his preſence from us, we muſt return into our firſt nothing. He is not far therefore from every one of us, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Athenians;</hi> nay, he is nearer to us, then we are unto our ſelves, <hi>tibi adſum, I am, I will be with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ye know there is a two-fold preſence of Almighty God. Firſt, his generall preſence, which is his univerſall power and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, whereby he governeth and diſpoſeth all things, both in heaven and earth, and under the earth, according to that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 139. <hi>If I climb up into heaven, thou art there, if I goe down to hell, thou art there alſo. If I take the wings of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and remaine in the uttermoſt parts of the ſea, even there alſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161734:7"/>ſhall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand ſhall hold me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, there is Gods ſpeciall preſence, whereby he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with his elect only, either to prevent their troubles, or elſe to comfort and ſupport them; and chiefly is he with his ſervants in his Temple, at his publick worſhip, which may eaſily be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained by an example. The King is, or ought to be, and I truſt, ſhortly will be, by his power in all parts of his Dominion; yet he is ſaid to be there, eſpecially where his Courtiers, where his retinue is. In like manner is the King of Kings by his unbounded power and providence at all times in all places; yet we may know him to be with us, after an eſpeciall manner in the Temple, from his retinue of heavenly Courtiers that are there attending on him. For it was not for ornament only, that the walls of <hi>Solomons</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were carved round about with Cherubims, but alſo to ſignifie that the holy Angels are ever about us at our publick ſervices. And if Angels be there, much more is the King of Saints, <hi>tibi adſum, I am, I will be with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are three things eſpecially that will continually be with us, the <hi>Aire,</hi> our <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Almighty God.</hi> We may as well be without our being, as without our breath; take but away this from us, and take away us too. The Aire leaveth us not till death, our Conſcience, this goeth further with us, it remaineth with us after death to all eternity. Doe not therefore the leaſt ſin, though none be with thee, but thine owne Conſcience, for this will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company thee to thy death-bed, nay, this worme will live to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. And thy conſcience is not more inſeparable from thee then Creator, whiſper never ſo ſoftly, he will heare thee, hide thy ſelfe never ſo cloſely, he will ſee thee, runne away never ſo ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he will ſtill be at thine elbow, <hi>tibi adſum, I am, I will be with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhould not ſpeak ſo much of Gods general preſence, his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall preſence is that which I muſt here inſiſt upon; that preſence which he promiſed the Patriarchs and Prophets, that preſence which our Saviour promiſed his Apoſtles, <hi>Loe, I am with you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, even unto the end of the world. Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>ult. Alway,</hi> there is no intermiſſion. <hi>To the end of the world,</hi> that is, world without end; here is no termination. We may have men for our compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, that will forſake us in diſtreſſe; or if they ſtick to us all our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161734:7"/>life, they muſt leave us at our death. But if God be our compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if God be preſent with us, it is not diſtreſſe, it is not death ſhall ever part us; nay, death ſhall unite us more neerly then ever we were before, we ſhall alway be with God, he will alway be with us, <hi>tibi adſum, I am, I will be with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if God be alway thus preſent with his Church, we may then expoſtulate here, as <hi>Gideon</hi> once did with the Angel <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Oh my Lord, if the Lord be with us, why then is all this befallen us?</hi> Why is the blood of his deare ſervants ſhed like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on every ſide? Why ſuffereth he the Turk and Pope to drinke themſelves drunk with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer; though ſeemingly God abſent himſelf from his Church for a ſeaſon, yet never will he finally forſake her; ſeemingly, I ſay, for indeed he abſenteth not himſelf at all, it is but in our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion that he is ever from us, if we can but beleeve it, he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with us alway, <hi>tibi adſum, I am, I will be with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the application of this now, may be two-fold.</p>
            <p>Firſt, here is comfort for all that mourn in <hi>Sion,</hi> and with good <hi>Hezekiah, turne their face to the wall.</hi> Let them be <hi>caſt into priſon</hi> with <hi>Joſeph</hi> and my Soveraign Lord the King, let them be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>dungeon,</hi> as <hi>Jeremy</hi> was, let them be caſt into a <hi>den,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> was, let them be caſt into the <hi>water,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> was, let them be caſt into the <hi>fire,</hi> as the <hi>three Children</hi> were, let them goe thorow fire and water, famine and ſword, never ſo many dangers, never ſo great diſaſters; yet ſo long as they have God with them, this will ſweeten all their pills, in the multitude of the ſorrowes which they have in their hearts, his comfortable preſence will refreſh their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing God is ſtill with us, this ſhould teach us like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to be ſtill with him, ſeeing he vouchſafeth to keep company with us on earth, therefore our converſation ſhould be with him in Heaven. When we are lying down to ſleep, to him we ſhould commit our Spirits; when we wake up, like <hi>David,</hi> we ſhould be preſent with him. It was <hi>Jacobs</hi> vow, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28: that <hi>if God would be with him, then the Lord ſhould be his God.</hi> We need not ſpeak ſo doubtfully, for God is certainly with thoſe that fear him, not only by his generall, but alſo by his ſpeciall preſence, to direct and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161734:8"/>protect them, to deliver and to defend them. Which leadeth me from the third part of the Text, the concomitant, Almighty God, to the fourth and laſt, which is the Churches ſafety, <hi>Flumina non operient, flamma non incendet, the Rivers ſhall not over-flow thee, the flame ſhall not kindle on thee; when thou paſſeſt thorow the waters I will be with thee, and thorow the rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee; when thou walkeſt thorow thee fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee. Flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I propounded four acceptions of theſe waters, ye ſhall ſee that the Church paſſeth ſafely thorow them all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, thorow waters, taken in the literall ſenſe. Sin had once ſo ſoiled the earth, that God was faine to lay it aſoak, it was ſo foul, that nothing would cleanſe it but a flood. There were Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants in ſinne, as well as in ſtature, the wickedneſſe of man was great in the earth. And <hi>abyſſus abyſſum,</hi> this depth of ſinne called for as deep a deluge, the flood-gates therefore were pluckt up, the windowes from on high were opened. And what diſtreſſe of nations was there then with perplexity, the ſea and the waves roaring, &amp; mens hearts failing them for fear? Me thinks I ſee how abruptly their marriage-feaſts are diſſolved, what haſte they make out adoores, that they may get up into trees, how ſome climb the tops of mountains, <hi>tamen ultra pergere tendunt.</hi> But the waters continually following them at heeles, when all hope that they ſhould eſcape drowning was taken away; me thinks I hear them curſe the day that ever they were borne, and wiſh, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that they might be metamorphoſed into fiſhes. But <hi>Noah</hi> found grace in the eyes of the Lord, when the flood was brought in upon the world of the ungodly; for though it rained as if hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth would have come together; though the waters were ſo grown, as to over-top the higheſt mountaine, yet hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens great Palinurus preſerved <hi>Noah</hi> in this ocean; <hi>flumina non o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perient, the rivers ſhall not over-flow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> may be a ſecond example, whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation was indeed farre ſtranger then <hi>Noahs,</hi> for <hi>Noah</hi> had a Ship, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had none, which made them think that there was no way in the world with them but drowning, <hi>Mars</hi> in the reare, and <hi>Neptune</hi> facing of them, they thought that one of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161734:8"/>theſe muſt needs devoure <hi>Iſrael</hi> with open mouth. But he that brought light out of darkneſſe, brought ſafety out of their greateſt danger; what they feared would be their deſtruction, this God made their preſervation, for rather then <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, <hi>Jordan</hi> ſhall forget his fluid nature, the flouds ſhall ſtand upright as an heap, and the depth ſhall be congealed in the heart of the Sea. Gods People need not fear the waters, <hi>the waters ſaw them and were afraid;</hi> and therefore run away with might and maine, to make way for them. The waters fared as if they had known the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> drowning the hoſte of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> but immuring the hoſte of <hi>Iſrael, flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> may be a third example to this purpoſe. There were never two greater Tyrants then <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> one drowneth the male Children, the other cutteth their throats. But as Chriſt eſcaped from <hi>Herod,</hi> ſo from <hi>Pharaoh, Moſes.</hi> His Parents durſt not long entertaine him in their houſe, when he was but a quarter old, they ſhipt him in an Ark of ruſhes. But how properly may that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> be applied to him, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 27.10. <hi>When my Father and my Mother forſake me, then the Lord taketh me up.</hi> Or rather, indeed the Lady did this, even the King of <hi>Egypts</hi> daughter, who named him therefore <hi>Moſes, Extractus,</hi> one drawn out, <hi>flumina non ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to theſe examples I may adde <hi>Elijahs</hi> and <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> paſſage over <hi>Jordan,</hi> the Diſciples with our Saviour in the Ship, and Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> moſt dangerous voyage toward <hi>Rome;</hi> all corroborating and confirming this aſſertion in our Text, <hi>flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord ſitteth above the water-flood, Pſal.</hi> 29.9. ye have heard the ſtory of him that wondred why any man would goe to Sea, ſeeing ſo many die at Sea; and that one replyed, he might wonder as well why any man will goe to Bed, ſeeing ſo many die in their Beds. <hi>Dii maris &amp; terrae,</hi> may be put into Gods Royall title, <hi>his way is in the ſea, and his paths in the great waters,</hi> he that was able without a ſhip, to walk ſafely on the Sea, muſt needs be able to ſave thoſe that goe down to the Sea in Ships, while they are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their vocation, they may be aſſured of his protection, he will <hi>give his Angels charge over them, to keep them in all their wayes;</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:161734:9"/>the Angel of the water mentioned <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.5. this Angell ſhall be their Pilot, and conduct them to their wiſhed haven, <hi>flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by <hi>waters</hi> we underſtood the enemies of the Church, neither ſhall theſe waters overflow her. The Serpents ſeed will ſtill be warring with the womans, the Dragon and his, againſt <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> and his Angels, the Church of Chriſt will ever be maligned by the Synagogue of Satan, but though theſe waters ſwell, yet they ſhall not prevaile againſt her. <hi>Davids</hi> enemies were daily in hand to ſwallow him up; but theſe waters of the proud had bounds, which they could never paſſe. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was both invaded and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> but how ſtrangely was he preſerved from him that had drunke ſtrange waters, and who with the ſole of his feet had dried up all the rivers of beſieged places! I have not time to ſhew you all the particular preſervations of Gods people, how he hath ſaved them ſtill from the reproof of thoſe that would have eaten them up.</p>
            <p>And from this experience of Gods former, together with the promiſes of his future favour, we may draw this application; we may here put on the reſolution of holy <hi>David, not to fear, though the earth be moved, and though the hils be carried into the midſt of the ſea, though the waters thereof rage and ſwell, and though the mountaines ſhake at the tempest of the ſame.</hi> Let the <hi>heathen</hi> never ſo <hi>furiouſly rage together,</hi> and let <hi>the people imagine a vaine thing</hi> (let them thinke to overthrow the government both of Church and State) let the <hi>rulers ſtand up,</hi> and <hi>take counſell together againſt the Lord, and against his Anointed,</hi> and againſt his Church, let <hi>Gebal,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and <hi>Amaleck,</hi> the Philiſtines with them that dwell at <hi>Tyre,</hi> let <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> Antichriſt and Mahomet, Pope and Turke, nay, let all the Devils in hell be confederate againſt the Church, yet ſtill ſhe ſhall be ſafe, the ſons of wickedneſſe ſhall not hurt her, the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt her, <hi>flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me apply this to the head of our Church, my Soveraigne Lord the King. The floods are riſen, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>the floods have lift up their voice, the floods lift up their waves.</hi> But theſe floods of ungodly Rebels ſhall not overflow Him, though the waves of the Sea are mighty, and rage horribly, yet the Lord (that's one
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161734:9"/>good turn) which dwelleth on high is mightier, and he will ſend down from the high to fetch him, he will take him out of many waters, he will make theſe Traytors, according to our common phraſe, <hi>as weake as water, as water ſpilt upon the ground, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be gathered up,</hi> he will ſtill the raging of the Sea, and the noiſe of his waves, and the madneſſe of the people, he will deliver the Kings ſoul in peace from the battle that hath been ſo long againſt him, he will deliver him from the ſtrivings of the people, and he will make him the Head of the Heathen; from the waters of ſtrife, he will bring him to the ſtill waters, the fierceneſſe of theſe men ſhall turn to his praiſe, and the fierceneſſe of them he will ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refraine, <hi>flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have ſeen, Solomon</hi> ſaid, and ſo have we, <hi>Servants upon Horſes, and Princes walking as ſervants upon the earth:</hi> but I hope we ſhall not much longer ſee this ſight.</p>
            <p>Water is a good ſervant, but a bad maſter: God therefore, I truſt, will ſhortly deliver us from the tiranny of an arbitrary A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, from the ſoveraignty of our fellow-ſubjects, <hi>flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by <hi>Waters</hi> we underſtood hereſies and doctrines of Devils; neither ſhall theſe waters overflow the Church. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill is ever changing Gods truth into a lie; if God have ſaid, <hi>ye ſhall;</hi> Satan will ſay, <hi>ye ſhall not die.</hi> And God ſendeth ſome ſuch ſtrong deluſions, that, as <hi>Eve</hi> did, they believe a lie, the Dragons floud of errours quite drowneth them in perdition: but the Church ſhall not miſcarry for all this Dragon-water, <hi>the earth</hi> (as it is <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.) <hi>ſhall ſwallow up the floud:</hi> the Earth, that is, the earthly minded, the ungodly of the world, ſhall ſwallow up the floud, that is, ſhall approve of, and entertaine theſe wicked errours. Not a little of this water hath been emptied into the river <hi>Tyber,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſwallowed down a great part of this Dragons floud. The reſidue hath been ſwallowed by <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Antinomians, Donatists</hi> and <hi>Novatians, Marcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> and <hi>Manichees, Socinians</hi> and <hi>Arminians, Preſhyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents, Browniſts</hi> and <hi>Burtoniſts, Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Familiſts</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> while we that are right <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> take in none but <hi>living water,</hi> drawing <hi>the water of truth</hi> out of the <hi>well of ſalvation,</hi> the floud of errour ſhall never ſurround or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161734:10"/>overwhelme us, <hi>flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, by <hi>Waters</hi> we underſtood the <hi>abyſſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation;</hi> neither ſhall theſe waters overflow the Church. One while the Devill telleth men that <hi>God is made up of all mercy,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while that <hi>his mercy is not ſo great as their ſins:</hi> firſt, he would flatter them into <hi>preſumption,</hi> then he would fright them into <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation:</hi> and when he hath brought them to this latter ſtate, then they are apt to drown themſelves, like that Lunatick which oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fell into the water, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.15. <hi>But the Lord</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptation. He will not ſuffer them</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>to be tempted above that they are able, but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that they may be able to beare it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Art thou come therefore into deep waters, ſo that the flouds are running over thee? hath Satan brought thee to the very brink of <hi>deſperation?</hi> why! yet he ſhall never be able to bring thee any further, if thou belong to Chriſt; he could not drowne the ſilly Swine without Chriſt's leave, (and thy Saviour will never licence him to doe thee ſuch a miſchief) he is but like a Dog in a ſtring, like a Dragon in a chaine, ſo that thou maieſt aſſure thy ſelf he can do thee no hurt without Gods ſpeciall warrant and commiſſion. Though thou walkeſt therefore through the valley of deſpair, yet fear no evill, for there is a way to Heaven juſt by the gates of Hell. It is the nature of clay to dam up the eyes, yet our Saviour put clay upon the blind to make him ſee. It is the nature of water to put out fire, yet <hi>Elijah</hi> poured water upon his ſacrifice to make it burne. God many times bringeth about his ends by means, which, to our thinking, are quite contrary. As he letteth ſome therefore (I mean the daring Rebels of our age) ſoare, with <hi>Ica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> upon the wings of preſumption, <hi>ut lapſu graviore ruant,</hi> that their downfall may be the greater, the heat of Gods wrath mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, as wax melteth at the fire, and they precipitating head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into the ſea of deſperation: So God ſuffereth others ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to fall into deſpaire, that the depth of miſery may invoke the depth of mercy, he throweth them, as it were balls againſt the ground, to make them bound the higher. When thou thinkeſt therefore he hath quite left thee, then he is neareſt to thee, when
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161734:10"/>thou walkeſt through the brooke of deſpaire, then he will lift up thy head, his rod and his ſtaffe ſhall conduct thee through theſe Stygian waters, <hi>Flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo ye have the ſafety of the Church in her former paſſage, which was <hi>per aquas,</hi> through the waters. Ye ſhall ſee her ſafety likewiſe in her latter paſſage, which is, <hi>per ignes,</hi> through the fire; when thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non combureris,</hi> thou ſhalt not be burnt. The Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.</hi> It hath therefore been the practice of perſecutours in all ages to burne up all the Bibles that they could lay hands on, knowing this to be the ready way for them to deſtroy the faith of Chriſt. But how ſtrangely hath the Bible ſcaped even in the moſt fiery perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though ſome part of it may be loſt, as the Propheſie of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch,</hi> and the Book of <hi>Iaſher,</hi> yet there is ſo much left ſtill, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in it all things neceſſary to ſalvation; God would never ſuffer all of it to be made fewell for the fire, <hi>non combureris, thou ſhalt not be burnt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> The damned in Hell are ever burning, never burnt. But who can dwell with thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting burnings? They could with a good will put up that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, <hi>hic ure, hic ſeca,</hi> that God would cut them all in pieces, and then burn them up to very nothing: But ſhould they make many ſuch prayers, there would none of them be heard, they ſhall not be burnt, the flame ſhall not kindle on them.</p>
            <p>But to come nearer to the Text. We propounded ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples out of Scripture, of men that paſſed ſafely through fire, literally taken.</p>
            <p>The firſt may be <hi>Lot.</hi> God uſually proportioneth the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the ſin. <hi>Sodome</hi> burned in luſt, and was therefore burnt with fire: but though brimſtone and fire were rained upon the Sodomites, yet God delivered <hi>Lot</hi> out of the midſt of the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, <hi>non combureris,</hi> thou ſhalt not be burnt.</p>
            <p>The ſecond example may be <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who came very neare the fire: <hi>Behold the fire and wood;</hi> nay, behold he is laid on the Altar upon the wood; yet for all this, God ſuffered not <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:161734:11"/>to doe him any hurt; he made an offer to offer up <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the will went for the deed, <hi>non combureris,</hi> thou ſhalt no be burnt.</p>
            <p>The third example may be the Iſraelites, in whoſe company the fire was kindled, <hi>there went out a fire from the Lord, and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the two hundred and fifty men that offered incenſe, Num.</hi> 16.35. But though the flame burnt up the ungodly mutiniers, yet every obedient Iſraelite eſcaped, <hi>non combureris,</hi> thou ſhalt not be burnt.</p>
            <p>The fourth example may be the three Salamanders in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. who though they walked through the fire, yet their coats were not changed, nor ſo much as the ſmell of fire had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on them. And this laſt example is without example, I never heard of any fire-proof before, for fire is of a moſt devouring and conſuming nature, turning all into its own ſubſtance that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neer it; yet the children of the fire, the ſparks, hurt not theſe three children, with the ſhields of their faith they quenched the violence of fire, when they walked through the fire, they were not burnt, neither did the flame kindle upon them.</p>
            <p>And to theſe I might adde, though ſomewhat out of order, the example of <hi>Abram,</hi> whom God brought out of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> of the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.7. Now <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r,</hi> as <hi>Hugo</hi> obſerveth, ſignifieth <hi>fire,</hi> the Greek word, from which our Engliſh word ſeemeth to come hath but one letter more: and therefore the Hebrews had a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that becauſe <hi>Abram</hi> would not worſhip the fire as the Caldeans did, he ſhould have been caſt into the fire, had not God given him notice of it. But though <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> ſignifie <hi>fire,</hi> yet the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gloſſe taketh it, not for a <hi>common,</hi> but for a <hi>proper name,</hi> for the name of the Towne or Village where <hi>Abram</hi> dwelt: This example therefore cannot claime kindred of the Text. I might more properly bring in our preſervation from the <hi>Powder-treaſon;</hi> but this is ſo beaten a path, that I will not tread it at this time. I will rather here anſwer a queſtion that may riſe from our Text, for is this promiſe alway performed, <hi>Thou ſhalt not be burnt, the flame ſhall not kindle on thee?</hi> what ſhall we ſay then to that fiery perſecution in Queen <hi>Marys</hi> daies, when there were ſo many <hi>Bethels</hi> in this Kingdome, ſo many Cities wherein mens bones were burnt?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, it is true, that the Church of Chriſt, this Church in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:161734:11"/>particular hath endured the <hi>fiery triall,</hi> but as <hi>Rex non moritur,</hi> ſo
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Regina.</hi> Pſal. 45.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſia non comburitur,</hi> as the King is never buried, ſo the Church is never burnt; <hi>James</hi> may die, and ſo may <hi>Charles,</hi> (yet God maintain his life) but the King (let Levellers do what they can) never dieth: So <hi>Latimer</hi> may be burnt, and <hi>Cranmer</hi> may be burnt, but the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s never burnt; If Pagans ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile ſo far (which God forbid) as to burn up all the Chriſtians; or if Puritans ſhould prevaile ſo far (which heavens hinder) as to burne up all the Proteſtants, yet I verily believe that out of their very <hi>aſhes</hi> God would raiſe up a new <hi>Phoenix, cinis martyru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſhould be <hi>femen Eccleſiae,</hi> the aſhes of an <hi>old</hi> ſhould be the ſeed of a <hi>new</hi> Church, ſhe ſhall not be ſo burnt as to be quite extinct, neither ſhall the flame ſo kindle upon her.</p>
            <p>And the application here of now may be briefly this. Seeing God wil not ſuffer his Church to be finally burnt up by others, this may teach us (as it were) to ſet on fire our ſelves, not with the fire of luſt, <hi>it is better to marry, then ſo to burn,</hi> nor with the fire of wrath, rather heap coales of fire upon the head of enemies; but let it be with the veſtall fire of devotion and affection, let our hearts burne within us with love to God and men; <hi>So ſhall neither the Sun burn us by day, nor the Moon by night, the Lord will preſerve us from all evill, it is even he that will keep both our bodies and our ſouls, when the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, when the Earth and the works therein ſhall be burnt up, he will preſerve and keep us from everlaſting fire, and exalt us to his</hi> coelum empyreum, <hi>his fiery hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, there forever to behold him whoſe eyes are as a flame of fire, and his feet like unto fine braſſe, as if they burned in a furnace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo ye have the ſafety of the Church in her paſſage through <hi>fire</hi> literally taken. A word or two of her <hi>ſafety</hi> as ſhe paſſeth through <hi>the fire of affliction and perſecution,</hi> when thou walkeſt through this fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee. The nature of fire is <hi>congregare homogenea,</hi> and <hi>ſegregare heterogenea,</hi> a Refiner therefore is wont to bring his mine to the fire, and by this means he ſevereth the ſilver from the drſſe; which is likewiſe the very practice of Almighty God, it is the Prophet <hi>Malachy's</hi> ſimilitude word for word, <hi>Malac.</hi> 3.3. <hi>He ſhall ſit as a Refiner and purifier of ſilver, and he ſhall purifie the ſons of</hi> Levi, <hi>and purge them as gold and ſilver.</hi> And the ſweet Singer
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:161734:12"/>of <hi>Iſrael</hi> harpeth upon the ſame ſtring, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.10. <hi>Thou, O God, hast proved us, thou alſo haſt tried us, like as ſilver is tried. Non ſicut foenum, ſed ſicut argentum, non in cineres convertiſti, ſed ſordes abluiſti,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> God trieth us not with a conſuming, but with a clenſing fire, turneth us not into aſhes, only taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our ſullage and our aſhes from us, purely purgeth away our droſſe, and taketh away all our tin. God purgeth men by affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as the Iſraelites were to purge the ſpoile of the Midianites, <hi>Num.</hi> 31.23. <hi>Every thing that may abide the fire, ye ſhall make it go through the fire, and it ſhall be clean.</hi> God trieth men by affliction what mettle they are made of; they that endure this fiery triall, they are good gold, they are Gods children; they that endure it not, they are but droſſe, they are but caſt-awaies. Good men are like <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> though they walk through the fiery furnace of affliction, yet they are not burnt up, no not ſo much as ſinged: but wicked men are like the Souldiers that bound and caſt them in, when they are yet but at the mouth of the fiery furnace, when the fire of affliction but beginneth to ſeize upon them, it prevaileth againſt them, and conſumeth them in a moment. Good men are, in this, like clay, the fire of affliction ſtrengtheneth and confirmeth them; but wicked men are like wax, as wax melteth at the fire, ſo doe the ungodly periſh in the fiery triall; affliction to them, is like the fire that burneth up the wood, and like the flame that conſumeth the mountaines; God maketh them like a fiery oven in time of his wrath, the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth them in his diſpleaſure, and the fire conſumeth them. Affliction maketh wicked men a great deale worſe, as water be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth much colder after heating, then ever it would have been, if it had never been heated. As for the righteous, it is not ſo with them, God burneth them indeed throughly, as the bricks of <hi>Babel</hi> were; but this is onely as a Potter frameth his veſſels in the fire, that ſo they may be veſſels unto honour, and for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters uſe, though they walk through the fire, yet they are not burnt, neither doth the flame kindle upon them. When <hi>Job's</hi> Wife heard of all the evill that God had brought upon her Husband, ſhe grew ſo mad, ſo outragious and impatient, that ſhe would faine have perſwaded him to make away with himſelfe: <hi>What,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>all that ever thou hadſt taken away from thee? is this the reward
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:161734:12"/>thou haſt for thine integrity?</hi> well, ſerve God who will, I would ſerve him no longer, make good the Devils words if thou wilt be ruled by me, doe, as he ſaid thou wouldeſt in ſuch a caſe, <hi>Curſe God, and die, Job</hi> 2.9. <hi>But ye have heard of the patience of Job,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>James,</hi> let his Wife therefore ſay what what ſhe will, he will have none of her counſell, <hi>thou talkeſt like an aſſe,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou ſpeakeſt like one of the fooliſh women.</hi> And indeed (as he goeth on, and as our Soveraigne by his moſt exemplary patience ſeemeth to ſay) <hi>ſhall we receive good at the hand of God, and not receive evill al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo?</hi> ſhall we receive health, and not ſickneſſe; wealth, and not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty; peace, and not war; honour, and not diſhonour; liberty, and not reſtraint? yes, my brethren, if we be Chriſtians we muſt endure all. And if we do this, then we may aſſure our ſelves that although we ſow in tears, yet we ſhall reap in joy, though God have ſuffered Rebels to ride over our heads, though we have gone through fire and water; yet, ere it be long, he will bring us and our Soveraigne out into a wealthy place; our light affliction which is but for a moment ſhall work for us a far more exceeding and eternall weight of glory, <hi>Which God of his infinite mercy vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to grant us, for the merits of his Chriſt, our Jeſus. To whom, with the Father, and the Holy Ghost, Three Perſons, one Immortall, Inviſible, Indiviſible, onely wiſe God, be rendred and aſcribed, as moſt due is, All Honour, Glory, Power, Praiſe, Might, Majeſty, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and Dominion, the reſidue of this bleſſed day preſent, and for evermore world without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
